<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This grammar has been deprecated - use FMPXMLRESULT instead -->
<FMPDSORESULT xmlns="http://www.filemaker.com/fmpdsoresult">
  <ERRORCODE>0</ERRORCODE>
  <DATABASE>DRIS-catalogue v3.6.fmp12</DATABASE>
  <LAYOUT/>
  <ROW MODID="12" RECORDID="148142">
    <TitleLargerEntity>Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</TitleLargerEntity>
    <Abstract>TCD MS 2327/64 is a letter from Catherine (Kate) D’Alton (née Phillips, of Clonmore, Co. Mayo, 1815-1853) to her husband, John William Alexander D’Alton (of Bessville, Co. Meath, 1792-1867).  Written during Catherine’s stay at Clonmore in 1824, between ‘Monday 9th of August’ and ’Friday 12th August’, and signed ‘Kate.’ The letter was cross written for reasons of economy: the text is written horizontally and vertically on the same page.
 
This letter forms part of: Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton, a collection of personal correspondence of some 275 letters sent between John and Catherine from 1818 to 1853. John D’Alton was educated at Trinity College Dublin and was an antiquarian, barrister, Irish historian, genealogist, and biographer.

The collection was donated to the Library of Trinity College, Dublin by Father Wallace Clare, St. Joseph’s College, Ipswich, Suffolk, on the 8th of  December 1951.

The following transcription of  TCD MS 2327/64 was made by Aisling Lockhart, Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College, Dublin:
Friday 12th August [1824]
My dear dear old own 
I received his dear letter the day before yesterday (Wednesday) my sweet fond if you knew how the sight of his dear writing delights my heart and so it ought for that is all I can see now of my poor darling I sent another letter to the Office for you the day I received yours which I suppose you are now reading as it is a little after 10 o Clock, my poor own in his study standing at the window how I wish I was near his old elbow (Saturday) I believe I will commence by replying to your dear old letter I think you end it as if you were a little vexed with me but my love you have no right to be so, if you read mine you would see that I had been at the post Office myself the day your letter came there and only missed of it by the post being unusually late that day however I forgive your crossness for I believe we both love each other too well not to be jealous of any seeming inattention -so my poor fond was dreaming his little Children were torn away from him they speak often of poor Papa and I delight to hear them do so for I think it would give pleasure to my darling if he heard their little chat –I saw the letter you wrote to Mamma on Toms return home , and think you did well to warn her, I myself committed it to the flames after I had read it Nurse likes the country I believe very well she is very attentive and takes exceeding good care of all the Children –Mamma would not let me get another maid as she has a Girl here as work woman who washes for the Children and brings everything up and down to the nursery As for Mrs Brennan I did not I believe mention her in any of my letters from Bloomfield however I now inform you that she is well Blooming and peevish and also that she is an old hag I dont like at all so you see I am answering your letter very exactly It was well you did not meet with a car, as Billy Kelly’s money was not to be had I am glad you went over to the Reades it will be a variety to you to spend an evening with them sometimes my poor Fond how lonely you must be at home particularly when your mother is ill she is a happy woman that has such a son as my poor old own for I believe there never was one more attentive to a Parent I honour him for it tho’ it now deprives me of him but please God he will be able to come to me soon to say the truth I think business requires you should come here now otherwise the necessary arrangements will never be compleated by all parties but if you were on the spot none would demur –There are such horrid pens and bad ink in this house that I almost fear my letters are scarcely legible. Tom is really an extraordinary being they are just on civil terms with him here but no cordiality between them I am I must own glad when I think that anything will make my own come down to me my fond tomorrow three weeks we parted from each other -and indeed they are the longest three weeks I ever pas[sed] dear dear own do come if you can at all and make your own happy with the sight of her own loved fond –Tom I believe wrote to you yesterday &amp; there is some demur about D’Alton taking the sub agency but as for the former he is an inconsistent creature and I would not mind what he says half a minute and D’Alton would I dare say get security &amp; if you were here yourself –I am glad Magan has written to you about the quit rent as I think the longer the right of it remains undecided the more difficult it will be to settle it &amp; as to your letter from Val Irwin I fancy you will find it very hard to execute his mothers commission for they are without exception the most disagreeable untaught boys exclusive of the science of epicurism I ever met with –you know she has a bad tongue herself when she is vexed yet you would be perhaps surprised at the degree of spite with which she speaks of the O Ferrals the cause of which I hear is some trifling inattention to Master John I am not a little surprised at your visit from Mr and Mrs Thom which was rather forward of her and ignorant of him I spoke to Tom about the rent roll &amp;c &amp;c more than once he says he has it ready to send you the first opportunity and that you may be sure will be as soon as I can get the wild fowl for you but the Grouse shooting does not begin until the 26th of this month and nobody is allowed to shoot until then how I wish I was to eat them with my poor own You ask how my uncle Myles and I met, he came to Mass here yesterday week (Sunday) We bowed slightly en passant but had no [ms damaged] communication during the day nor has he been [ms damaged] since My dear old own how it frets me you should be so lonely and sad I believe indeed as you say you feel like an orphan without me but my old own I hope will soon be with me again and who shall then part us Ah! Own dear I dont know how I ever consented to this journey without you I hope you take care of yourself my darling and that you don’t forget eating Stirabout –now and then I was reading Buchan’s domestic medicine here the other day in which it was strongly recommended also a simple Electuary which I copied and will make for my own when I go home to him and I know he will take when it is made by his poor owns old paw. I am glad to hear Betty stays quiet, but with respect to Williams bed cloathes I think it very odd she should not miss the blanket sooner you have dated that part of your letter Monday the day fortnight after I left home and I believe you discharged William either that day or the next she must at all events be very careless of her business if she left the bed so long without making it tell her so and also that she must air it once a week either in the Garden or at the Kitchen fire &amp; turn it every day tell her also if I hear of anything she has missed I shall consider her accountable for it as she does not mention it in proper time. I certainly did not put up the blanket -, so my poor old own has not been able to bespeak his black cloathes, now my darling dont neglect getting them the first money you get my poor fond thinks of himself last of any one but indeed he ought to be taken the most care of the poor own old Darling –Monday you nasty old fond I sent yesterday to the post office in hopes there would have been a letter there for me but there was none my own I long to hear from him how does your Mother get on I was dreaming of her all night but do not tell her so –We breakfast as late as usual here it is now near eleven o Clock and none of them down yet Charles McDermott and his cousin Miss Shiel of Ballyshannon rode over here to breakfast yesterday and spent the day she is a nice merry little Girl but has grown up very plain tho’ one of the prettiest Children I ever saw Charles is as great an original as ever and gave us a long romantic history of an adventure as he called it but which was nothing more than meeting a talkative old woman in a bog this he lengthens out with fine words and sentences for nearly two hours -and ended it with saying that it was a pity such brilliant parts and in fine such a woman should be buried in a Cabin –You are much mistaken if you expect to get any books from him, he is more choice of them than ever his father was –he lent some old Magazines here the cover of one of them was torn off (a blue paper one) and he was as fretted about it as you or fusty would be at loosing some valuable Black letter Manuscript –We had also Mr Joseph McDonnell here yesterday and his Nephew little Jones of Banada a very nice little boy Billy and he were very great but Eliza was quite frightened at Mr McDonnell and would not stay in the room at all she is such a pet with Anne that I am afraid she will spoil her she is beginning to make almost as great a noise about her when she leaves the room as she did after Celo and sleeps with her every night Mr McDonnell intends returning to Boulonge Sur Mer immediately and I think a certain friend of ours would have no very strong objection to accompany him if he could but this is only a conjecture of my own –for he does not speak of it even if he could –he set off last night to a supper at Dough Castle in a heavy rain, you would laugh if you heard old Dennis who was a little tipsy advising him not to go, and that he ought to be more consequential of himself -Miss Shiel did not go home last night but Charles did and is to return for her to day I shall send this letter to the Office by them as they return I was reading Rob Roy these two or three days do you recollect Celia Fitzgerald lent it to you some days after we were married and old own and I tried to read it in the study but I did not half attend to it I was so happy with poor bold but now that he is far away from me it amuses me very much there are some beautiful passages in it do you recollect particularly the night that Rob Roy passes in the highlands with Francis Osbaldist on and the account he gives of himself to him particularly when a thought of the future destinies of his sons flashes across his mind Walter Scott is certainly a very clever man yet after all he writes very carelessly sometimes –Have you heard anything from Baldwin since I last wrote to you? surely if he persists in his objection to anonymous publications you will have no objection to puting your your name after that Reble Lord of yours dont be cast down I hope he will yet be successful as he undertakes his present Campaign under your guidance he will fight with more skill than he did in former times -[ms damaged] you seen Mrs Bellew yet and what do you think of Maria O Kelly I hope Mrs Reynolds’s will not provide for her as quick as it did for Miss Brennan I am (thank God) quite well of my cough and want nothing to make me as happy as I am well but my own dear fond this is a sad dull county and I have no news to tell you but that Catherine o Connor is to be married this day to a Mr M-and are to set off after the ceremony for Dublin on their way to France Mr Cooke the priest who dined here yesterday was talking of the old Castle of Roscommon, I was thinking of your hero, and the Goodly company you had assembled within its walls –dear old own I think of you or of something concerning you every minute and always –This is such a wet day I fear I will get no one to take this letter to the Office but indeed it is now always raining in these mountains –dear Darling own come to me if you can I did my best to make what you wrote about be settled here but I suppose Tom wrote to you why it was not settled don’t be vexed with his folly whatever he has written 
Monday 9th August 1824 Tuesday
 I could get no one to go to the office yesterday as Tom is going there and tells me you may get it tomorrow if he is there before the mail goes off my own darling adieu ...but come if you can dear dear own adieu Billy &amp; Eliza send you Kisses and also their orders to come to them as well as your poor old troublesome Kate.

</Abstract>
    <Bibliography/>
    <CALM/>
    <CatNo>MS2327-64</CatNo>
    <Citation>IE TCD MS 2327/64</Citation>
    <CopyrightNotice>Copyright 2017 The Board of Trinity College Dublin. Images are available for single-use academic application only. Publication, transmission or display is prohibited without formal written approval of Trinity College Library, Dublin.</CopyrightNotice>
    <Description/>
    <DrisDocumentNo>MS2327-64_folio _ </DrisDocumentNo>
    <DrisPageNo>folio _ </DrisPageNo>
    <DRISPhotoID>MS2327-64_0</DRISPhotoID>
    <DrisUnique>0145514</DrisUnique>
    <Europeana>No</Europeana>
    <FormatDur/>
    <FormatH/>
    <FormatResolution/>
    <FormatW/>
    <Image>No</Image>
    <Introduction/>
    <LCN/>
    <MetadataCreationDate>22/10/2018 09:12:57</MetadataCreationDate>
    <MetadataModificationDate>07/12/2018 07:53:11</MetadataModificationDate>
    <PageNo/>
    <PageNoB/>
    <PageTotal>1</PageTotal>
    <PageType>folio</PageType>
    <PageTypeB/>
    <ProjectName>1822</ProjectName>
    <ProjectNo>Project 1822</ProjectNo>
    <Provenance>Donated to the Library of Trinity College, Dublin by Father Wallace Clare, St. Joseph’s College, Ipswich, Suffolk, 8 December 1951.</Provenance>
    <Publisher>A Publisher Name</Publisher>
    <PublisherCity/>
    <PublisherCountry/>
    <Sponsor/>
    <Title>Letter from Catherine (Kate) D’Alton, Clonmore, 8th-12th August, 1824 to John D’Alton</Title>
    <TitleLargerEntity2/>
    <TOC/>
    <Type>text</Type>
    <TypeOfWork>objects</TypeOfWork>
    <Visibility>COLLECTION/OBJECT</Visibility>
    <AttributedArtist>
      <DATA>D’Alton, John, 1792-1867</DATA>
      <DATA>Clare, Wallace, 1895-1963</DATA>
    </AttributedArtist>
    <AttributedArtistCalculation>
      <DATA>AttributedArtistRole: Addressee;AttributedArtistRoleCode: rcp; Attributed Artist: D’Alton, John, 1792-1867</DATA>
      <DATA>AttributedArtistRole: Donor;AttributedArtistRoleCode: dnr; Attributed Artist: Clare, Wallace, 1895-1963</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistCalculation>
    <AttributedArtistRole>
      <DATA>Addressee</DATA>
      <DATA>Donor</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistRole>
    <AttributedArtistRoleCode>
      <DATA>rcp</DATA>
      <DATA>dnr</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistRoleCode>
    <CopyrightHolder>
      <DATA>Public domain</DATA>
    </CopyrightHolder>
    <CopyrightNotes>
      <DATA/>
    </CopyrightNotes>
    <CopyrightStatus>
      <DATA>Expired</DATA>
    </CopyrightStatus>
    <SourceMaterialCopyrightStatusCalculation>
      <DATA>CopyrightStatus: Expired; CopyrightHolder: Public domain; CopyrightNotes: </DATA>
    </SourceMaterialCopyrightStatusCalculation>
    <Culture>
      <DATA>Irish</DATA>
    </Culture>
    <DateCalculation>
      <DATA>DateType: start; Day: 08-08-1824 A.D.</DATA>
      <DATA>DateType: end; Day: 12-08-1824 A.D.</DATA>
    </DateCalculation>
    <Dateday>
      <DATA>08</DATA>
      <DATA>12</DATA>
    </Dateday>
    <DateMonth>
      <DATA>08</DATA>
      <DATA>08</DATA>
    </DateMonth>
    <DateType>
      <DATA>start</DATA>
      <DATA>end</DATA>
    </DateType>
    <DateYear>
      <DATA>1824</DATA>
      <DATA>1824</DATA>
    </DateYear>
    <Era>
      <DATA>A.D.</DATA>
      <DATA>A.D.</DATA>
    </Era>
    <ISOCalculation>
      <DATA>start 18240808</DATA>
      <DATA>end 18240812</DATA>
    </ISOCalculation>
    <Language>
      <DATA>English</DATA>
    </Language>
    <LanguageCalculation>
      <DATA>Language: English; LanguageCode: eng</DATA>
    </LanguageCalculation>
    <LanguageTermCode>
      <DATA>eng</DATA>
    </LanguageTermCode>
    <LCSubjectNames>
      <DATA>D’Alton, John, 1792-1867--Correspondence</DATA>
    </LCSubjectNames>
    <Location>
      <DATA>Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College Dublin</DATA>
    </Location>
    <LocationClaculation>
      <DATA>LocationType: repository; Location: Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College Dublin</DATA>
    </LocationClaculation>
    <LocationType>
      <DATA>repository</DATA>
    </LocationType>
    <Medium>
      <DATA>paper (fiber product)</DATA>
    </Medium>
    <OpenKeyword>
      <DATA>D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859--Correspondence</DATA>
    </OpenKeyword>
    <OtherArtist>
      <DATA>D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859</DATA>
    </OtherArtist>
    <OtherArtistCalculation>
      <DATA>OtherArtistRole: Author; OtherArtistRoleCode: aut; OtherArtist: D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859</DATA>
    </OtherArtistCalculation>
    <OtherArtistRole>
      <DATA>Author</DATA>
    </OtherArtistRole>
    <OtherArtistRoleCode>
      <DATA>aut</DATA>
    </OtherArtistRoleCode>
    <OtherTitle/>
    <RelatedItemCalculation>
      <DATA>RelatedItemType: host; RelatedItemIdentifier: 0145515; RelatedItemTitle: Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</DATA>
    </RelatedItemCalculation>
    <RelatedItemIdentifier>
      <DATA>0145515</DATA>
    </RelatedItemIdentifier>
    <RelatedItemTitle>
      <DATA>Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</DATA>
    </RelatedItemTitle>
    <RelatedItemType>
      <DATA>host</DATA>
    </RelatedItemType>
    <SeriesReportNo/>
    <SubjectLCSH/>
    <SubjectTMG>
      <DATA>Correspondence</DATA>
      <DATA>Manuscripts</DATA>
    </SubjectTMG>
    <Support>
      <DATA>ink</DATA>
    </Support>
  </ROW>
  <ROW MODID="20" RECORDID="148149">
    <TitleLargerEntity>Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</TitleLargerEntity>
    <Abstract>TCD MS 2327/87 is a letter from John William Alexander D’Alton (of Bessville, Co. Meath, 1792-1867) to his wife, Catherine (Kate) D’Alton (née Phillips, of Clonmore, Co. Mayo, 1815-1853). Written on the 5th and 6th of September 1819 (Mullingar and Kealtown)  and addressed to Mrs Dalton, Upper Rutland Street, Dublin, in which John D’Alton reflects on his boat journey northwestbound along the Royal Canal from Dublin, and advises Catherine on how to spend the £15 he has sent her. The letter was cross written for reasons of economy: the text is written horizontally and vertically on the same page.
 
This letter forms part of: Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton, a collection of personal correspondence of some 275 letters sent between John and Catherine from 1818 to 1853. John D’Alton was educated at Trinity College Dublin and was an antiquarian, barrister, Irish historian, genealogist, and biographer.

The collection was donated to the Library of Trinity College, Dublin by Father Wallace Clare, St. Joseph’s College, Ipswich, Suffolk, on the 8th of  December 1951.

The following transcription of  TCD MS 2327/87 was made by Aisling Lockhart, Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College, Dublin:
TCD MS 2327/87
Direct to me to Mullingar still &amp; write tomorrow night or at farthest after tomorrow and you will 
have a letter from me on Saturday Boat ½ past 7 – 5th Septr 1819
My ever dear darling It is said and I believe with justice that the accounts which are written in the style of Journal (or rather in this case as I write by the hour of heurenal retain too many trivial circumstances whereas if a person suffers a few days to elapse the memory settles the important facts appear transparent while particles of no value are precipitated as sediment -on this theory I should not begin my letter so soon but I believe every little thing will delight my own fond -and I would deprive myself of the recurrence of enjoyment if I were to give you my letter wholesale and not in retail -I will not describe what I felt at parting you know it in your own heart -I could have wished to kiss my little own this morning but it would be shortening precious minutes of ours and might but distress her -take care of our little playfellow hereafter -Sure my poor mother was not jealous of me -It was the first morning I ever left home without a kiss from her too -but I stood by her bed and prayed I might meet her and you well again &amp; soon -I sent Betty &amp; Susan to [illegible] for you at the vegetable market -and felt myself comparatively happy in a monopoly of the first Cabbin which however I did not enjoy long -at the first lock just at Glasnevin Bridge there are heavy repairs making and we had to change our Boat -in the one to which we were transferred beyond the breech I found two gentlemen -who I believe continue to Mullingar -at present they annoy me not a little by their loud conversation and occasional heavy strides on the deck -No Cormacks here -One of my comrades has just made me laugh by a pun in my own style -he was reading the Way Bill &amp; remarked to his Companion that it was a blackguard thing to Kill-a-she-though I preserved hitherto a dignified silence I could not but smile -You know I believe what a lazy correspondent I am and how hard set I find myself at times to make out a page or two -yet when I write to you a thousand and a thousand things press upon me and I am more at a loss for time than for thoughts -These gentlemen are gone on deck By a notice of the interesting evolutions of a hawk who is darting I hear at birds full view -but I will not leave my snug tete a tete with yourself as I consider this -I stood on the deck while I could view Dublin while I could imagine the part where my adored little girl was but when I saw it fade like the baseless fabric of a vision -I returned under hatches -the Youths have returned and an additional man (elderly) the conversation turned on the Royal Canal Debentures all agree in my opinion that they are only to be stirred at an election time -but let my mother do nothing till I go up -Here come the breakfast things so I must adjourn ______ ½ past 12-Breakfast as is usual in the Boat produced conversation &amp; acquaintance -and I almost regretted the departure of the two young men who got out at Maynooth -leaving me to worse than solitude the society of the old &amp; vulgar fellow aforesaid -I find he is a Mr Bagnal Contractor for supplying the Boat with horses -a necessary animal still notwithstanding steam and acceleration -I used this man with no ceremony at ½ past 10 immediately after the departure of the youngsters I took out my French Prayer Book and read my 
prayers with more fervour as I thought you might be offering up yours at the same time -after that I 
took a little trot on the Banks of the Canal which has warmed me and however you may feel in poor Dublin let me tell you a little animal heat is not unpleasant here there is a fine child on deck (a second cabiner) about a year old that interests me now not a little sprawling on the deck as I trust one day to see dear Mazouki do on the parlour Carpet -½ past one the Porter in the second Cabin is beginning to operate there has been in the last hour a fight and a proposal of marriage -I was obliged by the loud tones of the latter to be an auditor of the whole negociation -the Gentleman stated his pretensions his quantity of ground his sacks of Potatoes his pigs &amp;c the Lady humoured him for some time -till at last she quaintly enough finished the whole by an exclamation of “Well but what will I do with my own poor man?” -I took out my thought Book and lost myself for some time in the little landscape my more than wife my darling fond had sketched on the blank page -dear own I trust you have not been caught in the heavy hail we have had in the last hour -Never go out I entreat you without an umbrella -An evening Post of last night has just emerged from the Captain’s pocket I will retire to it for a short time -3o’ clock The evening post turned out to be the London morning Chronicle of 30thAugust -and I am relieved from a listless perusal of its advertisements by the appearance of the Cloth &amp;c for dinner -a Cold shoulder of mutton is laid on so I will be feasted [ms damaged] we are already an hour late in our time so I think it probable we wont be into Mullingar till past eight o clock in which case I will sleep at your friend Mrs Clarke’s -It may be for the better -I must now put up my paper as the dinner begins to smell strong -Ah where is my own now -God preserve her wherever she may be -½ past 4 I take advantage of the temporary absence of my [ms damaged]chum to resume my letter to own but I know not when his reappearance may in politeness compel me to stop -Our Captain furnished us with so fine a fowl &amp; a nice piece of Bacon that we scruple to eat asunder the shoulder of mutton and left [ms damaged]...bly a reserve for another day and by us not unshaped -[ms damaged]drank your health in the silent language of the heart [ms damaged] times -When a man writes according to the wants that occur [ms damaged] strange connexions and transitions will appear on his paper and perhaps none more extraordinary than to pass as I do now from you to physic -But Mr Bagnal has acquainted me that he found the 
greatest antibilious benefit from taking now and again a bottle of a liquid sold like Soda water &amp; not unlike it in taste &amp; agreeableness but called Magnesia water which is sold in Crampton Court -and I beg you will make some memorandum for me to try it when I go to town at least to inquire about it -
he spoke so much of it The evening has cleared up and all at present is sunshine -but though I assure you I am not drunk I dont just now see as far as my bed -or in other words where I shall sleep -not where I wish in any case -I have just stopped to drink your health solemnly &amp; my mother’s &amp; poor Mazouka -Ah I will pray that I may soon see you all again -once for all observe wherever Mazouka occurs I have left 3 kisses on the word for my little darling -so you see her nine already -when you pay them tell her I sent them -though she may not understand you her Guardian angel will -I hope you will never omit evening prayers say a little prayer for my return in silence -Kealtown Monday morning 9 o’ clock -I have not been able to write to you since -a number of circumstances occurred -first a suspicious looking female in the second Cabin of our boat tendered a note of [illegible] which the Captain thought a forgery &amp; detained her on various pretences till he inquired further about it in Mullingar -I know not the result -Second the maid of the Boat hooked an acquaintance on me she was Mary whom my mother may remember serving to Mrs Mark in Dorset St-Third a drunken plebeian passenger just as we were entering Mullingar late enough in all conscience fell overboard his struggles in the water were horrible but a pole being put out to him he was saved -the delay did not end there -the Captain took out the man’s pocket Book least those about him might Kill him -and he called on me to witness the Contents he thereby became responsible for and though it was with great difficulty the man could budget to pay for what he ordered -we found in his Book £37 -but by this delay I did not leave the Boat till past eight -Maher did not meet so of course did not receive my letter I suppose -I was therefore obliged to have my vellisse carried to Sheridan’s whence Isent out to Clown that Maher should be prepared for sale that day -and I walked on by the road you &amp; I had posted to Kealtown -I sent another messenger from Poll Gilluns the woman I introduced to and arrived at Kealtown at about ½ past 9 -All well here-and the Doctor here -he was my bedfellow last night &amp; a great deal a better one than Francis -I have been pestered all the morning with inquiries -Murry from Clown has just brought me my vellisse and I retired on pretence of sorting some things in it-Mary Gee had left this yesterday -It was lucky I sent to Maher last night or the only Auctioneer in the town would have been engaged -½ past ten -Before I set off to Clown I write these four lines -Breakfast is over I finished half a Cold duck &amp; some hanged Beef so dont fear for my appetite -I was dreaming all last night of you &amp; little own -I thought she suddenly spoke &amp; smiling in my face called me dear Papa -the little pigeons who are just cooing before the door remind me always of her eugh do I spell the sound any way intelligibly -The Doctor seems to lay close siege -but Susan as well as I can observe keeps very distant to him -but I have not been called into consultation yet and I hope will not -as matters are so long hanging on -I have just returned (1/2 past four) from Clown where I did a great deal -and will I believe have money for you tomorrow -I walked first over the place which I reached on foot before 12 o’clock and am happy to say that every thing there looks thriving -four good little cabins have been built by Morris, Lynch, Marry and Maher -even Gibbons has part of one up -When the police man and auctioneer arrived I proceeded to sell Master Gibbons he threatening me in the usual stile but I not saying one word -I went through the sale and disposed of his corn to a man in Mullingar for not only one Year’s Rent -but also for five pounds penalty -Drivers and Auctioneers fees to the amount of 13 shillings and Maher’s charges for watching to the amount of £1..7..0 -so Maher made well of that job -when I had finished the sale Gibbons said he would never suffer any man to draw a blade of the Corn but blow out his brains -in consequence of which I had to get an order from a magistrate for two police men to watch it -to night &amp; protect its delivery to the purchaser -I had to go to three before I got this order think even if L’Estrange that refused it -but he is a mere Idad (my mother will explain this word to you -in consequence of the threats the purchaser very naturally would not pay me till he got the crop safe off -but I do not think Gibbons will dare to resist now -I then [illegible] returned along the Banks of the Canal reading my Revolution Chronology and thought of you when you scorned walking with me while I read and penulled -take that -I was overtaken by a woman who affected me much her name was Farrell -she was mother to a young man who proposed to me two years ago for a part of Clown -and whose death since that has I think deranged his mothers intellect -I then went to Ballinea to inquire about Hulton the surveyor I wished-but I hear he lives entirely at Sir Richard Nagles -I will write to him by Sir Richards boy who passes this way every day to the post -and whom I will have watched -but as I must write that note now &amp; make up the accounts of the day -&amp; still worse as I find dinner is come up I must quit you but you see I dont eat the bread of idleness -¼ past [ms damaged]has been he[re] -but as I told him this day I would from [ms damaged]trample him as I would the day under my feet -[ms damaged] try me with other materials he brought his wife -I pity the creature sincerely -even Gibbons fell on his knees before all -but I know not what I can do -I must be in Clown tomorrow --in consequence of this –Tell my mother Duignan and Nolan are still there at her service but very little at mine -I almost forgot to tell you that Doctor Swift electrified me not a little to-day for he called me aside to-day and when I expected some very different communication he told me (for I had been telling him in the might of 
my biliousness) -by no means to take a mixture of rhubarb and magnesia -Poor man he is better natured than bred -I delivered my letter for Hulton this night to the proper person but I do not expect an answer till Saturday -I must go out to tea and to be bothered for songs Tuesday morning. ¼ past seven I am awake after a tolerable night even with Francis for the Doctor went off yesterday I 
have only room to acknowledge receipt of yr letter and my pleasure at Mazouki’s recovery I am hurried off to Clown Gibbons has bullied the constables &amp; will not allow a Gap to be broke to carry off his crop -Tis done I have myself broke down the Gap -and the cars are going away loaded -You see there is nothing like resolution I told him if he attempted to resist me I would trample him under my feet as I did that Gap dont fear he is totally afraid of me I assure you –This letter is long enough 
to be illegible tell me if you could read it –I sent you £15 for I am now paid by the purchaser of Gibbons corn With this pay Mrs Hanlon Mrs Barry and the man sewer tax and any other taxes that may be called for and [?buy] in Candles &amp;c and let my mother pay Brennan -but don’t pay the Kings taxes yet or Moffatt or Doherty -buy in your Candles soap and all you want before you pay any debt &amp; dont pay Mrs Barry if you have not enough to [illegible] in &amp; tell me what you pay -Give 5 shillings Mr Nugent for Mrs McGuinness -if you chuse.

</Abstract>
    <Bibliography/>
    <CALM/>
    <CatNo>MS2327-87</CatNo>
    <Citation>IE TCD MS 2327/87</Citation>
    <CopyrightNotice>Copyright 2017 The Board of Trinity College Dublin. Images are available for single-use academic application only. Publication, transmission or display is prohibited without formal written approval of Trinity College Library, Dublin.</CopyrightNotice>
    <Description/>
    <DrisDocumentNo>MS2327-87_folio _ </DrisDocumentNo>
    <DrisPageNo>folio _ </DrisPageNo>
    <DRISPhotoID>MS2327-87_0</DRISPhotoID>
    <DrisUnique>0145521</DrisUnique>
    <Europeana>No</Europeana>
    <FormatDur/>
    <FormatH/>
    <FormatResolution/>
    <FormatW/>
    <Image>No</Image>
    <Introduction/>
    <LCN/>
    <MetadataCreationDate>23/10/2018 12:08:03</MetadataCreationDate>
    <MetadataModificationDate>07/12/2018 07:54:16</MetadataModificationDate>
    <PageNo/>
    <PageNoB/>
    <PageTotal>1</PageTotal>
    <PageType>folio</PageType>
    <PageTypeB/>
    <ProjectName>1823</ProjectName>
    <ProjectNo>Project 1823</ProjectNo>
    <Provenance>Donated to the Library of Trinity College, Dublin by Father Wallace Clare, St. Joseph’s College, Ipswich, Suffolk, 8 December 1951.</Provenance>
    <Publisher/>
    <PublisherCity/>
    <PublisherCountry/>
    <Sponsor/>
    <Title>Letter from John D’Alton, Mullingar and Kealtown, 5th and 6th of September 1819 to Catherine (Kate) D’Alton</Title>
    <TitleLargerEntity2/>
    <TOC/>
    <Type>text</Type>
    <TypeOfWork>objects</TypeOfWork>
    <Visibility>COLLECTION/OBJECT</Visibility>
    <AttributedArtist>
      <DATA>D’Alton, John, 1792-1867</DATA>
      <DATA>Clare, Wallace, 1895-1963</DATA>
    </AttributedArtist>
    <AttributedArtistCalculation>
      <DATA>AttributedArtistRole: Author;AttributedArtistRoleCode: aut; Attributed Artist: D’Alton, John, 1792-1867</DATA>
      <DATA>AttributedArtistRole: Donor;AttributedArtistRoleCode: dnr; Attributed Artist: Clare, Wallace, 1895-1963</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistCalculation>
    <AttributedArtistRole>
      <DATA>Author</DATA>
      <DATA>Donor</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistRole>
    <AttributedArtistRoleCode>
      <DATA>aut</DATA>
      <DATA>dnr</DATA>
    </AttributedArtistRoleCode>
    <CopyrightHolder>
      <DATA>Public domain</DATA>
    </CopyrightHolder>
    <CopyrightNotes>
      <DATA/>
    </CopyrightNotes>
    <CopyrightStatus>
      <DATA>Expired</DATA>
    </CopyrightStatus>
    <SourceMaterialCopyrightStatusCalculation>
      <DATA>CopyrightStatus: Expired; CopyrightHolder: Public domain; CopyrightNotes: </DATA>
    </SourceMaterialCopyrightStatusCalculation>
    <Culture>
      <DATA>Irish</DATA>
    </Culture>
    <DateCalculation>
      <DATA>DateType: start; Day:  05-09-1819 A.D.</DATA>
      <DATA>DateType: end; Day: 06-09-1819 A.D.</DATA>
    </DateCalculation>
    <Dateday>
      <DATA> 05</DATA>
      <DATA>06</DATA>
    </Dateday>
    <DateMonth>
      <DATA>09</DATA>
      <DATA>09</DATA>
    </DateMonth>
    <DateType>
      <DATA>start</DATA>
      <DATA>end</DATA>
    </DateType>
    <DateYear>
      <DATA>1819</DATA>
      <DATA>1819</DATA>
    </DateYear>
    <Era>
      <DATA>A.D.</DATA>
      <DATA>A.D.</DATA>
    </Era>
    <ISOCalculation>
      <DATA>start 181909 05</DATA>
      <DATA>end 18190906</DATA>
    </ISOCalculation>
    <Language>
      <DATA>English</DATA>
    </Language>
    <LanguageCalculation>
      <DATA>Language: English; LanguageCode: eng</DATA>
    </LanguageCalculation>
    <LanguageTermCode>
      <DATA>eng</DATA>
    </LanguageTermCode>
    <LCSubjectNames>
      <DATA>D’Alton, John, 1792-1867--Correspondence</DATA>
    </LCSubjectNames>
    <Location>
      <DATA>Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College Dublin</DATA>
    </Location>
    <LocationClaculation>
      <DATA>LocationType: repository; Location: Manuscripts &amp; Archives Research Library, Trinity College Dublin</DATA>
    </LocationClaculation>
    <LocationType>
      <DATA>repository</DATA>
    </LocationType>
    <Medium>
      <DATA>paper (fiber product)</DATA>
    </Medium>
    <OpenKeyword>
      <DATA>D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859--Correspondence</DATA>
    </OpenKeyword>
    <OtherArtist>
      <DATA>D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859</DATA>
    </OtherArtist>
    <OtherArtistCalculation>
      <DATA>OtherArtistRole: Addressee; OtherArtistRoleCode: rcp; OtherArtist: D’Alton, Catherine (Kate), approximately 1795-1859</DATA>
    </OtherArtistCalculation>
    <OtherArtistRole>
      <DATA>Addressee</DATA>
    </OtherArtistRole>
    <OtherArtistRoleCode>
      <DATA>rcp</DATA>
    </OtherArtistRoleCode>
    <OtherTitle/>
    <RelatedItemCalculation>
      <DATA>RelatedItemType: host; RelatedItemIdentifier: 0145515; RelatedItemTitle: Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</DATA>
    </RelatedItemCalculation>
    <RelatedItemIdentifier>
      <DATA>0145515</DATA>
    </RelatedItemIdentifier>
    <RelatedItemTitle>
      <DATA>Correspondence of John and Catherine D'Alton</DATA>
    </RelatedItemTitle>
    <RelatedItemType>
      <DATA>host</DATA>
    </RelatedItemType>
    <SeriesReportNo/>
    <SubjectLCSH>
      <DATA>Royal Canal (Ireland)--History--Sources</DATA>
      <DATA>Royal Canal (Ireland)--19th century--Description and travel--Anecdotes</DATA>
      <DATA>Inland navigation--Ireland--History--Sources</DATA>
    </SubjectLCSH>
    <SubjectTMG>
      <DATA>Correspondence</DATA>
      <DATA>Manuscripts</DATA>
    </SubjectTMG>
    <Support>
      <DATA>ink</DATA>
    </Support>
  </ROW>
</FMPDSORESULT>
